<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<LanguageData>

  <!-- Work tab control -->
  <AP_AutoModeLabel>Auto</AP_AutoModeLabel>
  <AP_AutoModeTabTip>When on, work priorities are reassigned automatically on a set interval (see mod settings). When off, press Optimize to assign once.\n\nMiddle-click to lock things so they're never changed automatically:\n- a colonist's name — that whole pawn\n- a column header — that work type\n- a single cell — just that one job\nLocked items show a padlock.</AP_AutoModeTabTip>
  <AP_Optimize>Optimize</AP_Optimize>
  <AP_RecalculateDone>{0} priorities updated.</AP_RecalculateDone>

  <!-- Settings: shell -->
  <AP_AdvancedMode>Show advanced settings</AP_AdvancedMode>
  <AP_ResetAll>Reset everything</AP_ResetAll>
  <AP_TabGeneral>General</AP_TabGeneral>
  <AP_TabScoring>Scoring</AP_TabScoring>
  <AP_TabWorkTypes>Work types</AP_TabWorkTypes>
  <AP_TabExternalWorkers>External workers</AP_TabExternalWorkers>
  <AP_TabPassions>Passions</AP_TabPassions>
  <AP_TipDefault>Default: {0}</AP_TipDefault>
  <AP_RevertTip>Reset to default.</AP_RevertTip>
  <AP_RevertWorkTypeTip>Reset every value of this work type to its default.</AP_RevertWorkTypeTip>

  <!-- Settings: general tab -->
  <AP_ReassignEvery>Reassign interval (hours)</AP_ReassignEvery>
  <AP_AutoIntervalTip>How often work is reassigned in auto mode. Longer is calmer — priorities won't chase short-lived events like a brief mental break. 24 = once per day.</AP_AutoIntervalTip>
  <AP_CoverageGuarantee>Guarantee minimum coverage</AP_CoverageGuarantee>
  <AP_CoverageGuaranteeTip>Keep every work type's minimum number of workers assigned, even when every capable pawn is a poor fit — so a colony never silently loses its only doctor.\n\nTurn this off to relax the guarantee: nobody is force-assigned to work they score badly at, but jobs may go completely uncovered, including Doctor in a small colony.</AP_CoverageGuaranteeTip>

  <!-- Settings: scoring tab -->
  <AP_SkillImportance>Skill importance</AP_SkillImportance>
  <AP_SkillImportanceTip>Weight of skill levels in a pawn's score. At 1.00, a level-20 pawn earns a full point from skill alone; higher values make raw skill matter more than everything else. This also sets the scale every bonus is measured against.</AP_SkillImportanceTip>
  <AP_RewardSpecialists>Reward specialists</AP_RewardSpecialists>
  <AP_RewardSpecialistsTip>How strongly a specialist's fit quality shifts their priority around the work type's importance. At 0 everyone assigned to a job gets the same priority; higher values give the best pawns visibly better priorities.\n\nIgnored for 'Everyone does this' and 'Always top priority' work.</AP_RewardSpecialistsTip>
  <AP_InspirationBoost>Boost inspired pawns</AP_InspirationBoost>
  <AP_InspirationBoostTip>An inspiration matching a work type's skills boosts that pawn's score and lifts the job's priority, so the inspiration gets used before it expires.</AP_InspirationBoostTip>
  <AP_AssignOpposed>Assign disliked work when needed</AP_AssignOpposed>
  <AP_AssignOpposedTip>Allow assigning work a pawn's ideoligion opposes when nobody willing can cover it. When off, opposed work is never auto-assigned — even if the job goes undone.</AP_AssignOpposedTip>
  <AP_UnskilledBaseline>Unskilled work baseline</AP_UnskilledBaseline>
  <AP_UnskilledBaselineTip>Score for work types with no relevant skills (Hauling, Cleaning, Firefighting...). Higher makes unskilled chores compete better against skilled work.</AP_UnskilledBaselineTip>
  <AP_CompareToBest>Compare to colony's best</AP_CompareToBest>
  <AP_CompareToBestTip>How much a pawn's standing relative to the colony's best counts versus their absolute skill (0 = absolute only, 1 = pure ranking). Relative standing is what spreads results across the whole priority range.</AP_CompareToBestTip>
  <AP_UseWorkSpeed>Use work-speed stats</AP_UseWorkSpeed>
  <AP_UseWorkSpeedTip>How strongly a work type's aptitude stats (work speed, carrying capacity, move speed...) shift a pawn's score. 0 = ignore stats entirely, 1 = multiply the score by them directly.</AP_UseWorkSpeedTip>
  <AP_OpposedWork>Ideology-opposed work</AP_OpposedWork>
  <AP_OpposedWorkTip>When an ideoligion-opposed pawn must be assigned for coverage, their fit quality is scaled by this before computing the priority. 0 = opposed assignments always land at the deepest priority.</AP_OpposedWorkTip>
  <AP_InspirationStrength>Inspiration boost strength</AP_InspirationStrength>
  <AP_InspirationStrengthTip>Flat score bonus while a pawn is inspired for a skill the work type uses. Large by design — inspirations are temporary, so the pawn should win the job while it lasts.</AP_InspirationStrengthTip>
  <AP_InspirationPriority>Inspiration priority</AP_InspirationPriority>
  <AP_InspirationPriorityTip>Minimum priority urgency (1 = top of the range) for a pawn's inspired work type, so an inspired job jumps the queue regardless of the work type's own importance.</AP_InspirationPriorityTip>

  <!-- Settings: work types tab -->
  <AP_ColWorkType>Work type</AP_ColWorkType>
  <AP_ColEveryone>Everyone</AP_ColEveryone>
  <AP_Importance>Importance</AP_Importance>
  <AP_ImportanceTip>How urgent this job is for the colony, independent of who does it: 1.00 maps to the top priority, 0 to the bottom of the range. Specialist quality then shifts individual pawns around this baseline.</AP_ImportanceTip>
  <AP_Everyone>Everyone does this</AP_Everyone>
  <AP_EveryoneTip>Every capable pawn gets this job at the importance priority (firefighting-style) instead of only the best few. The specialist options are ignored while this is on.</AP_EveryoneTip>
  <AP_MinWorkers>Minimum workers</AP_MinWorkers>
  <AP_MinWorkersTip>Coverage guarantee: at least this many pawns are assigned even if their scores are poor, as long as anyone capable exists. Also caps how many ideoligion-opposed pawns may be drafted in for coverage.</AP_MinWorkersTip>
  <AP_SpecialistCutoff>Specialist cutoff</AP_SpecialistCutoff>
  <AP_SpecialistCutoffTip>Capable pawns scoring below this are not assigned at all — specialists only, unless they're needed to meet the minimum workers.</AP_SpecialistCutoffTip>
  <AP_MaxWorkersShare>Max workers (share of colony)</AP_MaxWorkersShare>
  <AP_MaxWorkersShareTip>Cap on how many colonists may be assigned, as a share of those capable (rounded up, never below the minimum workers).</AP_MaxWorkersShareTip>
  <AP_AlwaysTop>Always top priority</AP_AlwaysTop>
  <AP_AlwaysTopTip>Pin every assigned worker to exactly the importance priority, ignoring quality spread — for life-critical work (Doctor) so it never sinks below chores on a wide priority range.</AP_AlwaysTopTip>
  <AP_PriorityFalloff>Priority falloff</AP_PriorityFalloff>
  <AP_PriorityFalloffTip>Each lower-ranked assigned worker gets one priority step worse than the one above, so the best pawn reliably takes the job first.</AP_PriorityFalloffTip>
  <AP_IgnoredWhileEveryone>Ignored while 'Everyone does this' is on.</AP_IgnoredWhileEveryone>
  <AP_IgnoredWhilePinnedOrEveryone>Ignored while 'Always top priority' or 'Everyone does this' is on.</AP_IgnoredWhilePinnedOrEveryone>
  <AP_IgnoredCoverageOff>Ignored while 'Guarantee minimum coverage' is off (General tab).</AP_IgnoredCoverageOff>

  <!-- Settings: passions tab -->
  <AP_MinorPassionBonus>Minor passion bonus</AP_MinorPassionBonus>
  <AP_MinorPassionBonusTip>Flat score bonus for a minor passion in the work type's most relevant skill. Also anchors the curve modded passions are derived from.</AP_MinorPassionBonusTip>
  <AP_MajorPassionBonus>Major passion bonus</AP_MajorPassionBonus>
  <AP_MajorPassionBonusTip>Flat score bonus for a major passion in the work type's most relevant skill. Also anchors the curve modded passions are derived from.</AP_MajorPassionBonusTip>
  <AP_PassionNoneTip>No passion is the baseline: no bonus, no penalty.</AP_PassionNoneTip>
  <AP_ModdedPassionTip>Score bonus for this passion. Its default is derived from the passion's learn rate ({0}x) and your Minor/Major passion sliders, so it keeps tracking them until you change it here.</AP_ModdedPassionTip>
  <AP_ModdedPassionTipPinned>Score bonus for this passion. Its default is a fixed value chosen for this specific passion.</AP_ModdedPassionTipPinned>
  <AP_BadPassionNote>This passion is flagged undesirable — by default it scores below no passion at all, steering work away from it.</AP_BadPassionNote>
  <AP_BadPassionPenalty>Bad passion penalty</AP_BadPassionPenalty>
  <AP_BadPassionPenaltyTip>How far below no-passion an undesirable modded passion (apathy, natural ineptitude...) scores by default. 0 = neutral. Vanilla passions are unaffected.</AP_BadPassionPenaltyTip>
  <AP_MaxPassionBonus>Max passion bonus</AP_MaxPassionBonus>
  <AP_MaxPassionBonusTip>Ceiling on the bonus a modded passion's learn rate can produce, so a 3x enthusiasm can't out-value skill itself. Values you set yourself on the sliders above are not capped.</AP_MaxPassionBonusTip>

  <!-- Settings: external workers tab -->
  <AP_ExtIntro>Take mechs and drones into account when assigning colonist work: where automatons can cover a job, colonists are pulled off it and freed for work only they can do.</AP_ExtIntro>
  <AP_AccountForMechs>Account for mechanoids</AP_AccountForMechs>
  <AP_AccountForMechsTip>Count your work mechs (Biotech lifters, cleansweepers, constructoids... and mechs from other mods) as workers, reducing how many colonists get the jobs they can do. Turn off to ignore mechs entirely.</AP_AccountForMechsTip>
  <AP_AccountForDrones>Account for drones</AP_AccountForDrones>
  <AP_AccountForDronesTip>Count utility drones (Vanilla Quests Expanded - Drone Factory) as workers, reducing how many colonists get the jobs they cover. Turn off to ignore drones entirely.</AP_AccountForDronesTip>
  <AP_AccountForGeneric>Account for {0}</AP_AccountForGeneric>
  <AP_AccountForGenericTip>Count {0} as external workers, reducing how many colonists get the jobs they can do.</AP_AccountForGenericTip>
  <AP_ExtOffload>Offload</AP_ExtOffload>
  <AP_ExtOffloadTip>How external workers change this job for colonists:\n- Off: ignore automatons here.\n- Reduce: hand some of the work to automatons but always keep the backup number of colonists.\n- Full: hand the job over entirely when automatons can cover it (no colonist backup).\n\nEither way, the colonists removed are always the worst-suited ones, so your best workers keep the job.</AP_ExtOffloadTip>
  <AP_ExtModeOff>Off</AP_ExtModeOff>
  <AP_ExtModeReduce>Reduce</AP_ExtModeReduce>
  <AP_ExtModeFull>Full</AP_ExtModeFull>
  <AP_ExtModeOffNote>Automatons are ignored for this work type.</AP_ExtModeOffNote>
  <AP_ExtBackup>Backup</AP_ExtBackup>
  <AP_ExtBackupTip>Colonists always kept on this job under Reduce, no matter how many automatons exist — a safety net if the automatons go offline. 0 = allow full offload.</AP_ExtBackupTip>
  <AP_ExtBackupIgnored>Only used in Reduce mode (Off ignores automatons; Full keeps no backup).</AP_ExtBackupIgnored>
  <AP_ExtUptime>Automaton uptime factor</AP_ExtUptime>
  <AP_ExtUptimeTip>How many colonists one full-time automaton is worth here. Above 1 because an automaton works continuously while a colonist splits their day across many jobs, sleep and breaks. Capacity is multiplied by this, then rounded down.</AP_ExtUptimeTip>
  <AP_ExtUptimeIgnored>Ignored while Offload is Off.</AP_ExtUptimeIgnored>
  <AP_ExtNoCategories>Turn on 'Account for mechanoids' or 'Account for drones' above for this to do anything.</AP_ExtNoCategories>
  <AP_ExtLiveNoCapacity>Right now: no external workers can do this on the current map.</AP_ExtLiveNoCapacity>
  <AP_ExtLiveCapacity>Right now: {0} capacity x {1} uptime — removing {2} colonist(s), keeping at least {3}.</AP_ExtLiveCapacity>

  <!-- Live math lines -->
  <AP_LivePassionLevels>Right now: worth about {0} skill levels.</AP_LivePassionLevels>
  <AP_LiveUrgency>Right now: maps to priority {0} on the 1–{1} range.</AP_LiveUrgency>
  <AP_LiveWorkStat>Right now: a pawn working 40% faster scores +{0}%.</AP_LiveWorkStat>
  <AP_LiveMaxWorkers>Right now: at most {0} of your {1} capable colonists.</AP_LiveMaxWorkers>
  <AP_LiveMaxWorkersExample>For example: at most {0} of {1} capable colonists.</AP_LiveMaxWorkersExample>

</LanguageData>
